hello and welcome it is November 1st
2023 and we're here in ACM live stream
55.1 discussing realizing synthetic
active inference agents really excited
and honored to have Magnus here for this
first discussion session we're going to
have have an interactive presentation
and then looking towards the do two have
a bit more open-endedness and maybe some
code execution maybe some message
passing live so thank you for joining
Magnus very excited for your
presentation and for this
discussion thanks I'm very very happy to
be here been looking forward to this for
for quite a while
now so um should I just get into it yes
right amazing so hi everybody uh I'm
Magnus I'm a machine learning research
engineer at versus and in a couple of
months also PhD graduate from bias lab
uh in
oven I'm here to talk about these two
papers realizing synthetic active
inference agents Parts one and two uh
that we did together with me and uh the
ever brilliant Ty Velar and B de
re all right um so one thing ahead of
time if you have like questions in the
chat or anything I can't see them but I
encourage people to interrupt me as much
as possible because it's more fun for
everybody if we can sort of have a bit
of a dialogue going have our own action
perception
Loop all right and with that out of the
way I clicked on my slides and they
changed so I think that part is
working excellent so this is like the
battle plan for what I want to go
through today um I want to start by
covering the problem statement that what
what are we trying to do with these two
papers what is sort of the the whole
idea and sort of serve you up the um the
point as it were right at the offset
then we're going to cover a bit of
background material and then we start to
get into the meat of the actual
papers which are mainly two things it is
uh what we call CFG notation so
constrained for uh for style Factor
graph
notation um and deriving uh messages
based on a local generalized free energy
functional so that we can um do this
efficiently and scalably all these nice
things that we want and then at the end
uh we're going to look at some
experiments that are in the two
paps uh to see whether this is all just
a nice theoretical exercise or whether
we actually have something that that
works all right let's uh let's get into
it so the main thing that I want to
do is we want to figure out how do we
put active inference on graphs is so the
big question that we're trying to get at
with these two
papers um because active inference is
awesome uh I think I can can say that in
this crowd uh and graphs are really
really nice and have some nice
properties um that we would like for
active
inference so let's a little bit deeper
into this what this actually
means right so I sort of put up uh two
things side by side here one being the
uh the active inference book and the
other being like a for stle Factor graph
of a state based model we're going to
try and compare sort of what we want out
of each
formalism so active inference great does
a lot of
things um but one thing that it doesn't
it the a very very classical 2015
original formulation which what I'm
mostly going to be referring to if we go
really by the books usually this is tied
to a pomdp model
structure um so that means we have these
discrete State space models and we
Define them with a b c d
matrices um and everything is sort of as
as we all know on love and this is great
we can do a lot of stuff with it but it
is still a choice that we make a
priority most of the
time the other thing is if we go
strictly by sort of the the original
planning algorithm there's a scaling
problem in the planning
Horizon that follows from us having to
do these large search trees that's
excellent work trying to address this
with the branching time active inference
uh parts of the sophisticated inference
uh program um all these really really
interesting developments using monol
research uh but sort of this isn't
really a solved problem yet
on the plus side what we do get that we
really really
want uh is that if we design an active
inference agent and we go by all the
nice things that we know and love we get
agents that are curious we get agents
that have this epistemic drive to go and
explore their world which is a really
really handy thing to have because if an
agent can gather its own information it
learn efficiently it'll sort of figure
out how to navigate and do things and
it's much easier to have the agent do
that rather than have us as Engineers
designers of the agent do
that right so we compare that to
building an agent using box standard uh
rational free engine minimization on a
graph we end up with an agent that
doesn't have exploration if I take this
type of formalism and I minimize free
energy and I can use that to construct a
controller I end up with a K control um
objective
and this is something that doesn't give
us this exploratory
drive we can get all sorts of other nice
things but we don't get this information
seeking behavior that is like a whole
Mark of active inference that we really
want the upside what we get is um a lot
a lot more
flexibility like I can write Factor
graphs for free form models and uh by
using message passing tools we can also
do inference in these models really
really efficient
it means we scale better uh again we
have more flexibilities in our model we
can do a lot of things but what we don't
get is this epistemic
drive so ideally what we would like is
want to take the Best of Both Worlds
right want to take all the good parts of
active inference and all the good parts
of sort of factor graph message passing
based free engery minimization and
squash them together to get one uh
unified framework for doing all the
stuff that we want so that be get to get
all the thumbs up and another thumbs
down uh everybody still with
me
excellent okay so to set this up because
these papers can get a little bit heavy
I'm going to try to walk through all the
different parts but s of set up the
whole framing of how this is going to
work going to start by reviewing a
little bit of of background material
it's not going to be too heavy I
promise
um and we're going to start with um our
favorite functional the variational free
energy again I think In This Crowd most
of you will have seen something that
looks like this uh
before and this is a fine way of writing
it we have some observations X and we
have some latence Z I'm going to use x
for observations and Z for Laten
throughout um and we're interested in in
minimizing this type of
Divergence this is great
however if we're in a position where we
have say multiple latens combined in
different ways and some parameters and
maybe a couple of different states and
things going
on this particular way of writing things
doesn't really sort of intuitively
capture all of that this doesn't
represent the underlying graph structure
of our
model so if we go uh up a little bit and
look at this guy here for instance
there's a lot of structure in this way
of writing a generative model see some
things are not connected to each other
uh things are there's a lot of things
going on here that we can't really
capture if we just stick with with this
way of writing our free
energy so the first thing we're going to
do is we're going to try and figure out
how do we write free energy and
graphs and to do that we're going to
need to have some
graphs uh and I like uh uh this
particular way of writing um my
probability graphical models there are
others uh this particular way is called
Aon style Factor graph and basically we
have three building
blocks we have squares which can
represent factors in a generative model
so this is going to be say p of x given
Z we have uh edges that we stick between
uh squares and they're going to
represent
variables this is a bit different to
what you would see if you do something
like a Bas Network where a note would be
a variable and you connect it to all the
variables that depend on
it um here the nodes are the factors and
the edges are the variables it's a
little bit of um of mental gymnastics if
you're not used to thinking in this
way and then if once we get into doing
inference with message passing I'll use
these little arrows to denote
messages as as they are flowing around
on a graph
and all of these three building blocks
is really most of what I'm going to use
until we get into it's all I'm going to
use until we get into the meat of uh of
the two
papers right so let's look at an example
of what this this could look like so I
have a pretty simple model
here this has three variables X Y and
Z and they factorize like
this so we have P of Y gets own Factor
variable y z given y this Factor
variable Z and x given Z this factor
rable
x so far so
good um all right so again this is just
a simple graph now we're going to try
and see if we can figure out how to do
how to distribute our free energy in
this graph how can we turn this General
formulation that we had of just some
ladance and observations into something
that we can you know put all over this
graph and this is the haest SL I
promise uh we got to do that by simply
saying well I have uh my free energy and
I'm gonna basically pick a term
associated with each node so I'm gonna
have a Q for each node and I'm GNA have
this I'm using f for just a generic
Factor you also think of it as like the
the P argument in in a normal free
energy and then we have this sum so this
sum here sums over all the nodes in our
model if you look here we have one two
three nodes so there's going to be one
term for each
node and that's really all that's
happening
here okay so far so
good this is
um not quite there yet because we're
going to need another term which going
to be this guy and what this basically
says is um subtract the
uh entropy of Right add add the entropy
of each Edge that is connected to more
than two nodes back in so why why would
we do this right I promise you there's a
reason
that this term if you don't s haven't
gone through the the ideas seems a
little at HW because now we have a free
energy for each node and we have this
extra entropy term for each Edge so
what's what's going on
there I I want to sort of illustrate how
that comes about and we get to this form
of the free energy which is a bey
approximation to the free
energy we can look at this graph you say
well look at this node
here Z given y I'm going to have a free
energy term and that free energy term
includes two
variables this node is connected to two
edges so the free energy around this
node will involve the variables that are
connected to that node
that means we get terms for y and get
terms for
Z but if we look at the other node here
this x given
Z that's also connected to two variables
it's connected to X on the one side and
z in the
other so if we do this summing up uh do
a free energy term for each
node this Z is going to get counted
twice it appears once in the blue side
and once in the red
circle so how do we get around counting
our variables
twice that's easy we just subtract it
again so that's why we get this extra um
entropy term coming in that's why we get
this guy because for each variable that
is connected to two
notes we're going to have this situation
Z is connected to two notes and
therefore it gets counted twice so we
simply get rid of one of
them does this make
sense
beautiful this is same thing as saying
that when we Define q in our free energy
functional we have this q log Q over
P we have a q that looks like this we
say Q of X Y and Z is going to be equal
to all these terms one for each note
there's one here for x and z there's one
here for Y and Z and there's one here
for
y matching the three
notes over these terms for the
edges and one for Z because it's
connected to two variables and one for y
because it's connected to uh two factors
and one for y because it's connected to
two
factors so that's really all this going
on here but if we do this and take this
Bey approximation to the free energy now
we can put the whole thing on a
graph right because we have in free
energy terms where every Noe and we have
entropy terms for every
Edge so that means now I can take my
free energy functional and I can
distribute it all over my graph and I
can work with everything
locally because if I'm interested in
updating Z here for instance check down
here Z appears here Q of x and z it
appears here Q of Y and Z and then it
has its own
marginal so basically like if the graph
were longer I can throw away everything
else
imagine we have like a um an an L
variable here for instance connected to
Y that doesn't influence Z in the
slightest like they're completely
separate on the graph they got a y in
between s of Mark of blank getting
everything
off so I can take what would be large
unwieldy problems involving lots of
variables and just turn them into lots
of small little local free minimization
problems it's really nice because we can
solve them locally
um and you know we don't have to deal
with the whole thing we can just worry
about all the little problems we can
string them
together um and get back reasonably good
solutions to uh to the thing we're
started
with um right so that is sort of the the
main procedure for how we would put free
energy on
graphs right take the free energy split
it into terms for each node and each
Edge
uh and then subtract whatever's double
counted Bey free energy really really
nice the other thing uh this allows us
to do which is something that um we go
into more in depth in in part two of the
papers is that we can do some
variational calculus tricks to derive
algorithms um that minimize this this
constraint Bey free
energy um and that allows us to say set
up the functional formal like Gren and
get excuse me belief propagation or
variational message passing or BL
propagation all these different
algorithms that we know and love just as
like from from a general
method and the spoiler is that when when
we go to part two and we start to derive
messages uh based on local generalized
free energy we're just going to use the
same
trick um
because as as as an engineer I'm kind of
a lazy person I don't want to remember
80 different algorithms I want to have
one trick my I want to do free an
minimization and I want to do it by
message passing and I want to have this
method sort of un loock down because
then my task is just to set up the right
generative model and make sure that the
INF problems are right and then I can
use that to do my smoothing or control
my robots or do my regression or
classification or whatever kind of thing
that I'm interested in again I only have
to learn one
tool which is really
nice all
right so uh you are the only person on
this call Daniel so I'm going to be
asking you uh what's missing from this
picture here of this graph you think
about your free energy functional what's
missing art hands th goes on and on
doesn't
it yeah there's a lot of um there's not
a lot of humanity in these graphs this
is like pure uh pure
engineering like the thing that this
graph represents really well is the
generative
model now you can write your P really
really
well you can't really write your
que no here this guy here exactly like
this guy here
which is the other sort of half of the
picture think about your free energy
functional Q over P have a Q and you
have a p but we can only write one of
them down the other half of the picture
thing that actually specifies our
inference
problem isn't really on this
graph
so if I want to write this on my graph I
want to make sure that my graph is
accurate representation of my inference
problem I don't have to go and and work
out some equations or read through like
a paragraph of text to figure out what's
going on how do you do
that and this is where we start on part
one up the two
papers
so um one way you can think of uh
defining your Q is that you can think of
of putting constraints on it I it has to
factorize in this way and it has to have
this functional form and these things
have to
normalize that that's a whole um sort of
set of mechanics that we can get into
but I haven't haven't planned to uh for
how these can work this is uh adding
this to your Factor graph effectively
allows you to specify uh the inference
problem because you can write out full
functional with all the constraints and
everything and minimizing that is going
to give you the the solution to to the
problem that you're interested in
okay so have a generic
graph and we don't really have a way to
put Q on right write P write my model
everything's great but I can't really
write
Q right I only have arrows I have
squares uh and I have lines those are
the only things that I'm allowed to work
with so to write
Q we need to introduce another piece of
not
ation and the piece that we've chosen is
this little gu little bead a little
circle I put variational marginal here
in in air
quotes just to say this represents some
entry in
Q so there's going to be one of these
for every node because we're using this
best the approximation where everything
gets distributed over the graph one for
every node and one for every
Edge we remember we had terms that
involve marginals around
nodes the model with uh X Y and Z we had
one for x and z and for um x x and z and
for Y and Z and we're going to have uh
little
beads for every Edge marginal I one for
x one for y and one for Z because these
are the things that we need to compute
these double counting
terms so if we take this generic graph
from
here and let's just add in beats that
denote all the little parts of q that we
want we're going to be left with
something that looks like
this so again what does it saying is I
have a marginal here around this note no
this little guy one on this Edge this
little guy and so on and so forth and
this just repeats for every node and
Edge on my graph
want to be really explicit about
it um towards the end of part two we do
like a compression step because this
gets unwieldy for large graphs but this
is sort of the
idea clarifying question here Magnus
what what values do the beads Andor
nodes and edges take on like we see the
structural topological layout and then
is each bead going to be like taking on
a number or is each bead taking on a
variable that doesn't have to be simply
a
number so each beat here is going to
present represent a posterior belief so
eest way to think about it there's going
to be an entry in
Q so if we go back to this model here
for instance we would have a beat that
represents qz that sits here so that
would be this term which could for
instance be like a categorical or a
Goran or a gamma or what have you uh
dependent on what falls out of INF
procedure have the same thing here and
we would have the same thing around here
again joint of X and C for instance
could be like a joint
caution um but these are going to be uh
probability distributions most of the
time okay so beads take on the semantics
of the node or the edge that they're
overlaid on and the beads give us a
little bit of a space between
p and Q quite literally because it
allows us to have this like
parallel Q bead
construction that inherits the structure
and the relationships of the generative
model drawn as a factor graph exactly
and that's because we start by
factorizing our Q over the graph we
split it into these nodes and Edge
specific um pum marginal
beliefs um that follows from the
approximation like the Bey thing we did
initially so that's where this structure
sort of follows from that's why we can
put this across the graph because we
started by saying well I'm going to
distribute my free energy Over My Graph
that's going to be my starting point so
then once we get into actually writing
out the free energy it would only
consist of terms that are local to bit
and pieces on the
graph I don't know who asked that
question but that's a good
one um and again I I encourage people to
interrupt me so if there are any more
questions let's let's just hit me now
I'll be watching the live chat but yeah
thank you all right
excellent right so the cool things about
having these beats explicitly
represented is that now we can start to
do stuff to
them um like for instance we can start
to factorize things in different way way
we can start to talk about well should Q
be forced to have a particular form like
should be forc it to be a gion for
instance um and that's sort of a lot of
the meat of the part one paper is just
showing different ways you can do this
if you want to write out um again Q as
well in your graph because if you have p
and you have
q with the constraints that tells you
everything you need to know about the
inference problem that you're trying to
solve that's that's the important part
because that instead of having to write
out stuff text and equations you can
literally draw your inference problem as
a
picture and like to me one of the most
intuitive and sort of most
practical uh set of of moves we do to Q
is that we mean field factorize
things that mean field just means we say
well I have my joint Q or we'll say here
XYZ and
V and I'm just going to set it to be
equal to the product for the individual
margins so I turn this thing turn into a
four four
variables into this thing the product of
four individual
marginals that's that's literally all it
is and I want to represent that
graphically that means I take one beat
for one Q just the single one here and I
just split it into four beats one for
each
q and now it's really I mean to me at
least it's really easy to see that I
have four different things going
on otherwise all the same rules apply we
stay inside the node because this is a
node marginal four connected
variables uh so they stay inside the
node um and yeah like that's one thing
we could
do but I a full mean field in this way
is it's also a bit aggressive
sometimes like so maybe you don't want
to factorize everything independently
maybe you want to re retain some joint
structure in in your marginals but you
can
do to do that then you end up doing
structured mean
field which I have two examples of here
so this is the same note that we had
earlier one giant Q joined over all the
variables but now I can for instance
split it into two sets of
two
right I have a a joint of X and Y and
have a joint of z and v so that would be
joint of X and Y and a joint over z and
v the trick here is that the edges that
represent the
variables they protrude through the node
border and sort of on that edge we put
the
Q inside the
node does this make sense yeah I'll just
restate it because I think it's it's one
of the key contributions of the
graphical notation yeah so let's just
say we were going to be drawing four
variables like rolling for
die one way to analyze that
statistically is treat all of them as
being drawn like all at once from a
four-dimensional distribution that's
unfactored and another extreme approach
aggressive approach would be treat them
as statistically independent or fully
factorized and so that was what was
shown on the previous
slide and now also there's Nuance where
you can say actually I think two of the
die have uh a a loose tether so I want
to infer The Joint distribution of these
two but leave these two independent so
now we can
see and clarify articulate all of the
space between UNF factorized and mean
field factorized and then we can
generate different graphs and ask like
well which structural
partitioning has what kind of
computational or runtime complexity what
kind of accuracy so then you can engage
in model selection across these
different
partitionings however seeing them all
visually as opposed to analytically
usually people are forced to just
represent either the unfactored or the
fully factorized because if you try to
represent things analytically with all
these partial factorizations on a large
graph it gets very
unwieldy yeah that's that's beautifully
put the idea is that we can treat some
things as you know being joint and some
things as being independent in
Q so the the underlying generative model
here is going to be the same it's just
how do we factorize our our belief we
want to do
inference that was those beautifully
put uh right that's that is one thing we
can do once we have an explicit
representation for
Q we can draw the beads that correspond
to the structure in our
uh irational
distribution but we can also put stuff
inside the Beats have like an EMP Circle
the same way I can write something
inside a node on my Factor graph I can
write something inside inside uh my
bead so what happens when we do that is
we enforce different form constraints um
on
Q here I just picked
one um where I'm saying well the Q on
this
Edge has to be a Delta
distribution that basically means that
when I do inference I'm doing like the
map estimate the arc Max of the variable
on this Edge
um and again if you go through uh a
bunch of derivations you'll find out
that that that that's what Falls what
falls out from here so that means that
now if I want to say um do map estimate
over my actions if I have an agent I can
put that into my
graph I don't have to write somewhere in
my paragraph text oh and then we do this
kind of thing and we Factor this way and
then we take the map estimate you know
you'll know at a glance
just from looking at the graph that this
particular variable and this particular
Edge has this functional form and
therefore it has to be a map
estimate you could do you could do this
with other things as well you could say
force it to be Gan or Wishard or
something else if you wanted um but this
idea of using Deltas is probably the
most common that I know of yeah this is
also very
nice and very consolidating the Delta
distribution is just a spike at one
location and so it's basically a single
data point or a value so it's like a
distribution that's kind of like a
distribution as a handle on a data point
so the Delta constraint is basically
passing one data point rather than a
full distribution through it's actually
a little there's a little subtlety here
um because you're completely right right
that if you have a a know a Delta
distributor variable centered at some
point that's a way you can enter data
but that also means you need to fix the
position of the Delta distribut a
variable which we do by calling it Black
this is how you would represent data
otherwise uh the position if a Delta
Spike becomes a thing you can
optimize and that's why it becomes a map
estimate because it is still a point but
you can put the point in the best
possible place which ends up being uh
the
map
so you're completely right um the form
of of a data point would also be a Delta
but then you also have to fix where this
Delta is
positioned to distinguish between the
two we do um data points data
constraints uh as filled black
notes and like Delta constraints uh I
map estimates um as these like unfilled
notes does that make sense
yeah free free Delta versus a fixed
Delta yeah exactly it's like saying you
have to be only here or you have to be a
point but you can put the point wherever
you
want all right uh
sorry sorry about that okay so question
and once again it's it's going to be a
new Daniel
uh now we can put three energy and
graphs and we can write out know Q we
can write out the entire inference
problem including constraints so we're
almost
there what is the thing that we're still
missing if we want to do active
inference on graphs like we want to go
back to the original question put the
whole thing on a graph what are we
missing the
environment yeah that's one thing
um usually we would like blanket that
off from our model so that would live
somewhere on the outside of our graph
but you're right there would be
somewhere um that we would have to
interface with an
environment but just in terms of the the
functionals that we want to to optimize
there still something
missing expected free energy or anything
prospective exactly that that's the
whole deal we've only been talking about
variational free energy so far and you
can get really really far with that but
one of the like core things that we want
out of active inference is we want to do
planning we want this information
seeking all this good stuff that we
started with the Curiosity and the the
sort of interest in the world around
you so how do we put that on a
graph
right and that's the next thing that
we're going to look at how do we put
this type of planning epistemic
functional on a
graph
okay what
know and to do that we're going to look
a little bit at how the EF actually
works so uh usually we denote an e by G
right uh that's that's like the common
notation and we write that as a function
of a policies we write Pi or in this
case I use U for my control variables so
I have U from sometimes St T up until
some planning Horizon capital T so that
means if I want to plan two steps in the
future uh capital T would be two and I
would
have um actions at either time
step does that make
sense awesome all right so the first
thing we're gonna say is well we compute
that by taking a sum of uh the free
energy at every time step that's the
standard way to do do
it if we expand that a little bit we get
a sum over risk term and an ambiguity
term just like we we all know on
love but the key
part the one that uh usually doesn't get
as much attention in this part here
usually we like to here again the
sum because the sum tells us something
important about uh the expected free
energy
it says us that this is a sum of a bunch
of independent terms so this function
actually
factorizes you think about it it means
we have one term for each time step or
if you write out the full graph it would
be one you know node on our
graph um and to compute the whole thing
that we're interested in we just sum
them
up so the actual object factorizes over
the
graph and that's kind of neat because it
means that when we we look at the way
this is constructed like from the get-go
there's already sort of a hint of how we
can go about putting it on a
graph and what we would need to
do is figure out well if I want to do
this around one node on my
graph how do I do it and do it in a way
that you know everything is consistent
and we recover all these nice objectives
and everything that we have already seen
before so how do we do that how do we
make uh a functional that's local to a
node that inherits all the nice
properties that we want out of an
expected or spoiler a generalized free
energy and we're just like we're just
going to go through and and
constructed uh so we're going to start
because we're working uh Under the
Umbrella the free energy principle with
a variation of free energy it's going to
be our first term
here and this going to be for some node
that's connected to two variables x and
z and then we also know that a lot of
the nice
epistemic drive that we we see in active
inference agents it follows from uh some
information gain term so we're simply
going to bold
on uh an information gain term that's
local to our
node and if we do that we we can we can
do something quite interesting
then so um up for for going through the
derivation
yeah SEC all right so the first thing
we're going to do is we're just going to
pull everything into the same integral
so both of these guys integrating over Q
of x and z q of x and z that means we
can we can put them together just do it
once then we look inside these brackets
and we go wait a minute we got two
logs we can pull all this inside the
log I think nothing fancy
here but then we look at this guy and we
go wait I have a Q like either side of
my line these two guys are going to
cancel divide something by
itself doesn't really doesn't really
give you much and if we do that then
we're actually left with the generalized
free
energy uh local to a node similar to
what Thomas par and uh friston
introduced in this 2019
paper so that means if we take our free
energy around a node which we can do
because we've already gone through all
the um the ration alha why that's a good
idea and we bold on uh an a negative
Information Gain
term we actually end up with the same
functional uh that was already proposed
uh in this amazing paper like four years
ago that's kind of
nice could you maybe Express what is it
about the negative Information Gain
that's doing the work the epistemic
work right so the way I I like to think
of it um is it's first of all it's
negative because we're minimizing we
really want to maximize Information Gain
but be minimizing our free energy or e
or whatever so we flip the
sign the other thing is you can rewrite
this into uh say a marginal entropy over
your States your
z uh minus a conditional
entropy over Z after you've seen X what
does this mean it means one of these
terms is going to encode how much
uncertainty is in uh like your Laten
variable your Laten State Z before you
do anything how uncertain are you right
now about
something and what you subtract from
that is the uncertainty after you've
seen some observation X and the bigger
that difference the larger your
uncertainty before getting an
observation and the lower it is after
the higher the Information
Gain so that's that's how I like to
think of why Information Gain sort of
gives us this exploration thing because
when we allow our agents to pick out
observations I we allow them to pick
what we should condition on we calculate
the information
gain and we tell them this is this is
what you're supposed to optimize they're
going to go look for the places you know
in the world where they are most
uncertain about what's happening and
where they predict that if they observe
something they're going to be the most
certain
and how how would you contrast this
expression with the decomposition of
expected free energy as pragmatic Value
Plus epistemic value so that's that's
the beauty of it right I don't actually
have to because what they what uh p and
friston also showed in this paper is
that if I do this uh
functional on uh the same ponp model
that we've used for everything else it
actually evaluates to exact same thing
as the expected free
energy so for all intents and purposes
it is exactly the
same so all inations about e are got a
map maybe this is looking a little ahead
but do you foresee that generalized free
energy
will come to rule them all and that we
won't talk so much about vfe and EF or
do you see those as still holding down
in important semantic
space I think it's an open question I'm
not um confident enough in in any of
this and especially not about the
future um to know how things are going
to turn out but I do know that if um I
take this
maneuver if I have a variational free
energy which I can use to recover
something like K control and I Bol on an
Information Gain term that gives me this
exploration that I like I can end up
with a generalized free energy um and if
you if you go through the proofs in part
two you also see that uh this makes it
easier to derive messages compared to
unexpected free energy because we we
tried the expected free energy as well
and it didn't really
work so like for this particular
application the generaliz free energy
works better as for any sort of
ontological status I'm uh
I'm just going to be an engineer what
about explicitly pragmatic aspects of
future time steps so if we have the vfe
embodying the real time pragmatism and
then we have an explicit future oriented
epistemic component where would we find
that kind of classical
EF flavor of pragmatic value of future
States as
well can I come back to that in like a
few slides um of course because I
actually have an example of what this
construction gives you if you want to
add in say a gold prior so you want to
add C Vector in the standard
nomenclature or basically like a a prior
over future desired
observations and that's uh the thing
that's going to power um all go directed
Behavior and the experiments as well
like the the the spoiler version is that
this ends up um if you work through it
you Cod
like take this note construction that we
came up with and you work out the
corresponding energy term that we would
use to calculate say your biry free
energy you end up with uh the exact
expression that you usually get for uh
expected free energy so you can actually
recover one to one the standard sort of
algorithm um by writing this on your
graph and and doing these manipulations
and then doing it in a particular way
you will get the exact same thing back
um but yeah hold on hold on to that
thought um because in a minute or two
we'll we'll get back to
it right okay yeah um this is another
thing so there are a couple ways to to
go through this um and to make it
exactly like uh I was to make it exactly
like the thing we find in um say uh
classical uh active inference papers
we need to do this kind of substitution
here so here I've uh basically gone to
the same get to the same results but in
a different way where mean field
factorized and then we exchange this Q
for this P that's is
important um so usually if you read an
active inference paper you see this uh P
of O and S and Q of s this joint here
denoted with something like Q with the
Tilt above
it and it just me means we substitute in
this particular part of our generative
model
um if you go through yeah this the
standard tutorial type things this would
be substituting in your a matrix for
instance and but we call this move a p
substitution because we're literally
substituting a p for a Q and we do this
because um but because we need to in
order to derive uh all the messages that
we need to be able to do this in a nice
distributed way and get to our end goal
of putting active inference on
graphs so I just want to introduce this
move here uh because it's the last bit
of notation um that we're going to
need to cover basically everything
that's in in part
one and the way we write this is
literally know if Q's are circles and
P's are
squares we are going to swap a circle
for a square so we
take the little bead here that
represents a
Q and we swap it for a square and this
Square means in the expectation of your
not local free
energy
substitute um P of this variable
conditioned on everything else that's
connected so you can see if we have we
mean field factorization
here QX QC QX QC and then we do a p
substitution we are left with the same
generalized free energy functional just
a different way of getting
there does this make
sense
awesome okay and that is like the main
meat of what we introduced in part
one so sort of to recap everything we've
done so far because we're moving at
quite a high
Pace we've taken um our free energy and
we put it on graphs we did that by uh
using a bey approximation so we have a
bey free
energy then we realized that we can
write down everything that we need to in
order to specify everything in our
inference problem we can't write down q
and we can't write down our constraints
on
Q so we came up with uh CFG constrained
uh for style Factor graph notation to
write down the entire inference problem
graphically then we figured out that um
the E factorizes which is great because
that means we can also treat it as
something that's local on our
graph and if we take not local free
energy kind of thing that would give us
K control if we did it
everywhere uh and we bold on an
Information Gain term we recover
something that looks an awful lot like
uh generalized free
energy uh that that Frist and Par
derived in 2019 which numerically ends
up like algebraically ends up evaluating
to the same thing as the expected free
energy so we have a version of expect
for these pumpy P mods I should say so
we have a version of the expected free
energy that is also distributed over our
graph is there anything that is relevant
to mention about discret versus
continuous time
models yes so we haven't done any of
this work on continuous time models like
these large generalized coordinate
filters with lapr approximations and we
haven't done that here um because the
base representation we're using is a
graph so when we want to do planning we
literally have to write
out uh explicit time steps for the
future um you could probably do
something like this for um you know the
whole continuous time active inference
as well but that that's a whole other
can of worms that we haven't dug
into um yeah so so far this is this is
only something that's been worked out
for like the discrete time case doesn't
have to be discret State spaces you
could work this out uh because we get
the general form of all the messages
could work this out for like continuous
variables if you
want um
but yeah continuous time is not
something we've done
yet all right I mean if there are any
other questions I think this is a good
time to pause because we're going to get
into the next sort of meaty section in a
minute I'll ask one question from live
chat upcycle Club
wrote How can synthetic active inference
agents be integrated with other
intelligence paradigms such as deep
learning or evolutionary algorithm
so beauty of how this ends up working is
this becomes another message passing
algorithm not even not message it
becomes like literally one sort of local
message out of the notes uh that we do
these operations to everything else is
going to function like box standard VMP
or uh belief propagation some product uh
sort of classical machine learning
tools and
so any a way you can usually combine
your problemistic graphical model with
uh deep neural net like youd have a deep
neural net power in your transition
Dynamics for instance if you wanted and
that wouldn't change anything here
because we're still only doing stuff
locally on a
graph so if
we uh do actually have a graph here that
shows
something I'm just going to go back to
one of the ear graphs because this is
probably the easiest way to illustrate
yeah this this guy here let's say that
we wanted to do all these operations
around this node here where we have like
a laden Z and we connect to some outside
world that we call X where we get our
observations all the operations are
going to happen oops inside the blue
circle everything that we do is actually
only going to fake the variables that
are connected to this node and around
this node so everything else everything
that's over
here is going to work exactly the same
way as with any other message passing
algorithm so you could hook this up to
say deep neural network if you've
trained it right uh and use that to say
be a note function somewhere
or um I suppose you could also use it
with with evolutionary optimizers uh
it's not something I've seen done a lot
but uh it's it's a cool idea and I don't
see any reason in principle why should
work because what we're doing really is
just changing the objective functional
around one of our nodes a little
bit does that uh does that answer your
question OB
cycle cool
continue all right let me get back to
where we
were whoops here right okay so this is
uh where we're going to look at how how
we add in something like a goal prior
because we had this like a little while
ago how do you get your goals and your
constraints and your objectives your
desires and and your agents Desires in
life as it were into the model how do we
do
that and the way we came up with of
doing it is that we Define this
composite
node so this is going to be again hold
on to your butts
this is uh this looks nastier than it
is really what we're saying is we have a
box on our Factor graph because again
all we're allowed to to do are lines and
boxes and arrows beats we have a box on
our Factor graph and inside this box
there's going to be two other
boxes we're gonna have this guy here
called P which could for instance
represent a likelihood model and we're
gonna have this guy here called P tilder
which is going to represent our goal
and that means when we go through the
motions of defining uh know Q around
this composite node with all our um
modifications and everything we end up
with um a model Like A
P that is not normalized it's going to
be P of x and
z
right yeah P of of x given Z is going to
be this node
times P Tilda of x given W in this case
if it has any
parameters well the basically means is
that we can add in a goal prior to our
model at the cost of it being not
normalized turns out that this not
really a problem that's not
normalized
um he but the basic idea is that if we
want to adding goals what we do is
simply we wrap our goals and our
likelihood in into you know one box on
our
graph and we just go through the
motions just sit down you calculate you
work through all the little bits pieces
and you push all your symbols around and
at the end the result you're going to
get uh is going to be something
useful so this is the way to to add in
goals you simply just you know Bol on an
extra factor to your model that that en
go your
goals okay I don't I don't know if this
is helpful but but check me on this it's
almost in like a racing game when the
high score has the ghost that is leading
the pack so we have like the goal prior
is kind of like the ghost in the midst
and then there's all the actual P but
then there's the Shadow and perfect
alignment or perfect fulfillment is when
the actual there's no space between the
actual and the preference so in the
textbook
analytical representation that would be
like P of O conditioned on
c yeah so we have the same it's just P
of X conditioned on
W H but it it works exactly the same
like if you I think that's also what we
call in the experiment if you go through
it it ends up just being the normal C
Vector um but you're right you're
completely right if you're doing a
racing game and you have say an
idealized perfect run as your ghost that
would be going in
here and you would sort of map out the
whole trajectory of where the ghost is
at all the time points that you want to
plan
over and then from here from the top
from the Z's is going to be your attempt
to recreate uh the perfect
run yeah which is actually an
interesting idea you could have some
kind of expert trajectory Define your
goals and then use that that to learn
the parameters of your model then do do
your planning from that that would
actually be a cool thing to try and
do but yeah um I think so far the
interations are like on
point all right so I'm just gonna keep
going I
think because one of the yeah one of the
questions that came up during uh thezero
live
stream uh was you know pull up a LMA and
be like what does this mean pull up a l
be like what does this mean and so on
and so forth so I've taking the liberty
of just putting on this graph what all
the lmers mean because then we can talk
about what they mean and if you want to
go through the n-r derivations they're
there in the
paper because again as I mentioned
earlier I'm a lace engineer I really
only have one trick um that is I can
know write out my free energy and I can
solve for stationary points and that
gives me message passing algorithms and
that that's all I
do so if you look at this graph here at
this node there basically three things
that we need to solve for need to solve
for
x what is the stationary Point here we
need to solve for Z and by symmetry that
also applies to Theta if this likelihood
Noe has any parameters for instance so
you could think of this as being like a
laden State and an a
matrix with like a der lay
prior and we need to solve for w which
is the parameters of our uh expert run
like our C Vector in the standard
nomenclature and if this node has any
parameters like whatever they may be
usually the standard form it doesn't but
you
could so really there's three things we
need to solve for this guy in the middle
stuff going out of this Noe and stuff
going out of this
Noe and it just so happens that there's
three lemas in the
paper there one that solves for this guy
he how do we update our predicted
observation which ends up coinciding
with uh how we would usually do it if
we're Computing EF which is
nice another LMA that says what should
the backwards message towards our state
be and this is this is going to be the
important one this is the what allows us
to do a lot of the really cool
stuff because this basically says if I'm
optimizing GFE EF
and I want to reason backwards from the
best
possible uh sort of outcome in terms of
balancing all epistemics and
everything what should that be that's
basically what comes out
here and we have a third
LMA that deals with you know the stuff
coming out the other way let's say you
want to update your goals let's say you
when you drive your run the ghost sort
of reacts to what you
do that's kind of the thing that would
be coming out here
and then we have two theorems uh that
show that the messages coming out here
and here um if you iterate them the
stationary points can actually be found
by fixed Point duration schemes I.E you
can solve this by message
passing so to recap the lemas are what
should these guys look like and that's
where you find the
messages and the theorum states that if
you do this you can actually uh solve
your problem and find these stationary
points uh by fixed point
iterations and this is this is a little
Technical and if you want to get into it
I encourage you to go and read the
paper um but the point being I'm still a
Las engineer still only have one tool I
can only solve for stationary points of
my free energy on my graph and if I do
that um I have three things to solve for
and I have to make sure that if itated I
also get something sensible out and
that's what the three lemas and the two
theorems are about
very nice
so Factor graph not just as
telecommunications message passing
infrastructure but as research
agenda and conveyance
puristic yeah because once you're in the
space in sort of this way of of writing
things are graphically you can write
your problem graphically and it's easy
to see how two things are different you
can also write something where you don't
know the solution
yet if you don't know the solution
that's a research
problem yeah and the dash lines and
then it's a great
pette thanks uh I hope it's also going
to end up being being useful because
again what I'm doing really here is that
you know we're presenting tools right
we're we're building stuff for other
other people to hopefully the
use and sort of the litmos test as to
whether this is going to be actually
practical for people who are interested
in building active inference systems and
Bing about active inference systems is
whether the people that are interested
in this actually end up using it
otherwise it's it's a need idea that
just ends up living in a
drawer so like I have a open invitation
to everyone if you're interested in
using this kind of notation I'll be
happy to help you with your graphs
because I think it's uh I think it be a
benefit if we can all agree in like a
unified way of specifying our problem
and it should be one that is not just um
geared towards towards
experts I should be able to write out
all the equations everything no that
should also be some something for us but
if you are interested in applying active
inference you should also have an easy
sort of intuitive Syntax for how to
write down exactly what it is you're
doing
um because if you do that then everyone
knows and then you know communication
becomes easy and writing out your
algorithm becomes easy and sort of
making sure that everyone knows at all
times what's going on becomes
straightforward because you know you can
literally read it off from the picture
so again an open invitation to anyone
who's interested in this like hit me up
I'll be happy to uh to take a look at
your stuff that's awesome I think one
more piece I'll add that's a very
prospective very pragmatic point to make
and also I believe that there's a great
opportunity for metaanalysis of the
literature and rederivation of these
kinds of graphs for the figures that
we've seen over the last 15 years and
then that will make a lot of continuity
because we can then bring the factor
graph motifs from models that are widely
discussed and kind of bring those into
the Next Generation
[Music]
and that's that's the hope and it's
funny that you say that out of all
things because if you look at what goes
on the next slide that's actually what
we
do like so this is a way of drawing um a
standard you know ano 2015 active
inference EF
evaluation uh as a constraint for in
style Factor
graph so that's like let's break this
down see what it
does because I mean I've been talking
for like an hour already and I've been
talking about
nothing most of what I've been talking
about is what all these boxes and little
bits pieces
mean so if we start at the very end and
I hope I'm pointing in the right
direction I don't know how I'm mirrored
in the screen but otherwise it's that
end um one of the things we would use to
define is a prior overwear agent St
starts which we denote by a d Vector
that's the standard way of doing it so
we want to add in a d Vector we put this
little square because there's a variable
that's clamed in P there like a
parameter that we don't mess
with you could update it and you could
indicate that in graph but here we
don't and we have this little guy that's
because know these two are going to be
different we don't have a joint of D and
Z we just have a z
we move on now we have this node which
I've labeled with T and T is for
transition this
indicates a discrete State transition
I.E a multiplication by a b
Matrix the B Matrix is what we find
here so what this is saying is we have
fixed an
action uh at time
T in order to move from Z at time T to
uh Z at t+ one it's just like a
multiplication by transition
Matrix then we have this
thing this is an equality node why do we
have an equality in the middle of
everything and that's because we're
using edges to represent
variables and an edge is a line like I
can only connect an edge to two
things so if I need my variable to
connect to more than two things I need
to create copies of my
variable if I want to create copies
that's the same as saying I have two
things three things and they're all
going to be the same they're all going
to be equal so this equality node says
this edge here and this edge here and
this edge here are all going to be the
same that's all it
does and we can keep going here from uh
Z at t+1 with a new action new
transition Z at T plus2 and so on and so
forth
that basically just you know
applies uh these transition
matrices but the really interesting part
is happening down here around what would
be a likelihood
Noe again we have this multiplication by
a matrix in this case it's going to be a
likelihood our a
matrix we have this composite node
construction where we have a goal prior
it's categorical parameterized by Z and
we have our observations
here right so this construction here is
what um oh yeah and we have this P
substitution we have these two guys
factorizing
separately uh so we have all the
constructions necessary to do our local
GF which in this case equals the
vve sorry the EF we have our goal prior
we have all the little ingredients and
bits and
pieces so how do we write given that we
have all this the exact same algorithm
as people were using
2015 we do that by adding in arrows
remember I had arrows as the last thing
way back when we
started and errors in this case describe
the schedule I which messages do you
pass and you can sort of follow these
along and see that you're kind of you're
rolling forwards through
time so this is like creating a roll out
and saying well what would happen if I
did that at this time well H go here
then what would happen if I did that go
here and so on and so forth so you get
this sort of forward
role uh as a function of a
policy I the series of matrices you fix
up
here and this composite node the energy
term of that node ends up being exactly
equal to uh you know one term of uh the
EF GF
in this model that we already
established factorizes over time so you
roll this thing out do your Forge roll
out take all the energy terms of these
composite notes and you sum them up and
that gives you back the exact algorithm
uh that's used to
evaluate e in like the very original
first types of
papers B so just to make a clarifying
point and then a question so for
comparison to the base graph and the
2022 textbook people might want to check
out figure 4.3 or figure
7.3 so here we' have already clamped B
so here we're just
evaluating one
policy because we see b as a black
square right because we need if we go by
like the the sort of Standard Version we
need to evaluate uh the EF as a function
function of a policy so we put in a
policy we do this roll out and we read
off our EV number and then you know we
take the softmax all fees and it gives
us you know a distribution
over policies that we can select from
and it's this roll out thing that um
makes the scaling hard because every
time you add a new Step you to go
through all your possible actions and
search tree branches and you get into
all these things that um people are
trying to solve in a whole host of
different interesting ways
but you're right we're treating policy
as something that's fixed because we're
evaluating e as a function of a policy
yeah and then of course you iterate over
your affordances over your policies to
calculate e for each and then you get
policy posterior and then you can do
what you will with the posterior yeah so
then it basically becomes like a model
comparison problem given this policy
this roll out and you know I get this
energy
terms um which one is the best
uh but it's funny that you say that
because one of the things that we also
do now that we have backwards
messages is that we don't have to fix
the
policy right think about it all the
stuff we're doing happens down here in
the little sort of Dash
box but the policy lives up
here we already established that
everything is local on the graph I can
do whatever I want down here it's not
really going to impact anything up
here so if I now turn these black
squares into random
variables I can still do
inference and I can still do inference
in a way that gives me back a
policy however now this policy is going
to be um one that
optimizes GFE or
EF uh locally these notes otherwise
everything is going to work as if you
were doing like a forwards backwards
kale control type
thing and what we need to do then is we
need to take all our candidate matrices
and we to put them into this mixture
model and that basically says
um if I have my indicator variable the
indicator variable picks out uh one of
the
Transitions and then you have uh you
want to infer the posterior over
indicator
variable such that
um yeah uh it it becomes a good
approximation for the probability of
selecting each uh particular Matrix at
this point in
time that did not come out clear did
that make sense at all yeah maybe
explain that in the context of why it's
called
TM uh it's TM for transition
mixture so it's like you have instead of
saying I do either you know action one
action two or action three I sort of do
a mixture of all of them and then I
weigh them uh according to uh well where
I should be going which is going to be
informed by these composite noes down
here the composite noes Bas tell you
where should you be going if you're
looking for like stationary points of
your generalized free
energy uh and these notes say all right
if this is where I'm going
this is the the transitions I should
take with this and this and this
probability okay maybe just to to
clarify and emphasize that what is the
policy selection
mechanism in direct policy
inference so that's actually one of the
the things that I really like about this
way of doing it
um you can pick whatever you want so we
do two here in in the paper one which is
this one
uh like the one that I have on on screen
here where you just you get a posterior
out over your policy and you can read
off you know the posterior over actions
at every time step and then it's up to
you whether you want to
sample what you want to do with it but
what we also show is that you can add
these Delta constraints on these edges
here that are labeled
you and if you do what you get back is a
series of map estimates over your
policy um the trick being that is now
something youve write as part of your
infant
problem
so as for the the the policy selection
mechanism what I'm going to say is we we
should in my opinion we should be
patient about it so if we get a
distribution over possible policies
that's uh that's the way it should be
and then you know you can do what what
you think is right with your
distribution yeah this is a very nice
point that the outcome of the EF
iterated across policies is a
distribution on
policy and so then you can simply
choose the best one you could choose the
worst one you could cut the deck in the
middle you you could do any number of
then secondary policy selection
policies and one that feels natural and
makes sense is just to take the first
order interpretation of the distribution
and then sample directly from that
distribution you could do that or I
think a very common thing to do is just
say the arcmax are you the best
policy at all time steps but yeah I
either one works um the point being
really that as you said instead of doing
this compute EF and then construct a a
distribution of a polies you just infer
the distribution of policies directly as
part of your inference
cool yeah and this actually allows us to
do something uh we don't really explore
too much in the paper but which I'm I'm
hoping to explore in the future which is
that we get rid of this combinatorial
explosion because if you look at the
kind of things you would have to do
there's a lot of messages going on here
but basically what you should take away
is that everything goes back and forth
on every Edge and when these two guys
Collide they give you the the posterior
distribution over uh over your policy or
over the action at that time is what it
to
say but because we're reasoning
backwards and we don't have to do this
for every
policy we scale linearly in time rather
than getting this this large
explosion like with the caveat that
there's some iterations going on and you
know there's some some root finding to
get these red messages F the right way
like there's some extra computation here
and there but this whole procedure
pretty much scales linearly in the
planning Horizon rather than you know
this giant exponential explosion which
to me is really nice because it hints at
us being able to do something that's
quite a lot bigger uh what we have done
so
far right here on this slide I'll ask a
question from Ryan who
wrote are we guaranteed convergence
after a single forwards backwards sweep
of the
messages no so this is an iterative
procedure this functions closer to what
you would get with a variational message
passing thing where you have to iterate
it a couple of
times um so no we're not guarantee
convergence after single Force backwards
pass usually that's probably wouldn't be
enough you would have to do like two or
three or something and those iterations
you use some other heris like how much
improvement you're getting and is that a
monotonic iteration
or do you ever
yeah so there's some work still to be
done on this so I can't claim like 100%
mathematical assurity but this seems to
function a lot like a variational
message passing algorithm where things
just nicely decrease as as you do more
iterations so therefore more iterations
is always better um but it's going to
hit like a convergence thing at some
point where the the gain of running more
iterations is going to be marginal
like that's that's how I I'm confident
this actually works but because we
changed the functional I'm not sure
whether all the like convergence proof
supplies I'm not I can't be 100% I'm
going to put it at like
98 yeah you'll never iterate worse you
ratchet and
improve but I guess my question is could
there be drop offs where you're
monotonically improving and then you
enter a new regime of another
Improvement
phase
yeah I don't I don't see why not I
haven't seen it but the the models we've
tested this on have been uh variations
of the teamas they've been quite
small um so there there's still work to
be doing actually exploring exactly how
this this algorithm uh
behaves um not like from theoretical
also from theoretical standpoint but
also just from like the Practical what
what actually happens if you start
running things and you build out models
and sort of getting a feel for how these
things work because doing it in this way
is not something that has has been done
before at least to my knowledge again
I'm going to hedge my bets a little bit
here all
right um are there any more
questions no good to carry
on keep going right because this is this
is what you actually get out if you run
this for a couple of iterations on the
teamas so the tmas environment is the
classic one that we all know one love
where we have a mouse our agent that
starts in this position in the middle
here and it's looking for a piece of
cheese piece of cheese is going to be
either in this left arm or in this right
arm um however at the back here is a
Q and The Q tells the mouse whether the
cheese is to the left or to the right so
the optimal thing to do is to go and
visit the queue first and then go check
out the correct
R and that's all of the the uh hello
world of this epistemic drive that we
like with active inference because an
active inference agent is going to go
and collect information and then go
either left or right whereas if you just
do some greedy uh fully gold directed
agent it's just going to gamble and
going other left and right and hoping
for the
best so if we do this s Direct policy
inference
um with know this this uh form like gr
and derive station Point like grch and
active inference type thing these are
the posteriors we're going to get out
and you see that uh the agent does
actually in planning only
replicate uh this this nice policy that
we want where it first
goes and samples the que and afterwards
it's indifferent as to which side to go
to but it know it's going to go to
either of the two
sites and this is something that's done
only using planning so the agent doesn't
actually get to execute anything and go
and and actually sample the queue and
update its
beliefs like in the absence of all that
it can still figure out that hey maybe I
should go and and check the queue first
before I uh I go find my
snack my Q is telling me to find the
[Laughter]
queue yeah I mean pretty much
um so again when I saw these results I
was very very happy because this shows
that all the the sort of heavy duty
theoretical work actually paid off and
yield something that uh replicates the
the standard
experiments that sort of is the Baseline
that we should be able to
do right what what the next thing we got
right yeah um so in part two we also
extend this to do parameter
learning um and what that means is we
want to learn the the a matri the
likelihood Matrix and we do that by
replicating the standard uh sort of EF
type um algorithm where we inference all
of this model and we compare free energy
of the model which includes these EF
terms for each policy so we can sort of
get the same type of thing with the
policy evaluation and evaluating
expected free energy and all these
things that we like um and the task is
whether we can figure out like we can
solve the task and we can
learn a matrix a what is the actual
mapping the likelihood mapping that we
want that's because the first experiment
relied mainly on this message the one
flowing out back towards the state
whereas this one also has a component of
this message flowing towards uh a
likelihood Matrix this ideally should
correspond to something like a to term
in like the classical or shorten back uh
formulation um which should drive our
agent to uh you know go and explore its
environment and figure out what's up and
then as we
iterate
um yeah as re iterate this back and
forth a couple of times we should learn
the the
mapping um and we see very very nicely
that uh free energy uh de increases the
minimum as we
learn uh gets lower and low and lower
except for these spikes here this is
when the agent actually gets its it
observation when
it gets its uh rewards it piece of
cheese that's because there is some like
some noise in the reward probabilities
it's not 100% so you can see every time
predicts a win but it gets a loss the
free energy
spikes which is
consistent if your model predicts
something and you get something else
your free Eng is going to be
off uh and if we compare to an agent
that does just box standard B free
energy variational free energy under the
Bey approximation you can see that
nothing really happens and it loses all
the trials because it's greedy it
doesn't go and gather the information
like the the information of the
queue
furthermore if if we look at the actual
sort of matrices that gets
learned uh these are the different
um locations that me the origin the left
arm the right arm and the Q
location uh and this uh row here
indicates whether the Q says go left Q's
go go right and this is whether the uh
reward is on the left or the
right this whether you get a reward
whether you get no reward
okay so basically what we can see is
that
if the que is on the right we also
predict that we're going to get the
reward on the
right get a reward on the right you know
we predict the reward is on the
right and so on and so forth we get a
reward on the left on the left basically
what this shows is that we are able to
accurately learn uh the mapping in the
uh in the
environment which is kind of nice
because again this means that our agent
will go and figure things
out um and actually learn how to to
navigate an environment that it doesn't
know okay so this is the final slide
that I have and I've been talking
forever now and the main sort of
take-home message that I like to leave
everyone with is
uh we can put active inference on
graphs that we can do that and that is
um and once we
do we are left with sort of this Lego
block approach to um constructing our
active influence
agents because everything is local on
the graph I can do my local manipulation
to get my my EF my GF down here and then
I can build out whatever graph I want in
all other directions I can have
hierarchies I can have temporal depth I
can do smoothing filtering I can do
control um I can do any combinations of
variables that I like as long as I can
figure out the
inference um it all
works and we can get uh the classical
things that we all know and love as
special
cases and we can solve inference on
these uh using standard tools from like
belief propagation or variational
message
pausing uh combined with these um new
messages that flow out of uh not that up
to my
G so this gives us at in my mind a a
flexible way to construct these large
sprawling uh fre form
models which in the end gets us you know
the best of of both WS we started with
get the epistemics we get free form
models and we have a recipe for doing
efficient
inference and that is everything I
got
excellent well let's have a little bit
more conversation and kind of ask a few
questions as we land the plane on the
dot one and then next time in the dot
two we'll return with maybe little code
little bit of drawing and some hopefully
some more people on the stream um okay
so what does synthetic mean to
you in this case it was sort of to um
underline that this is from an
engineering point of view the noce I
didn't really talk anything about brains
or basent mechanics or individuation and
Niche construction all these other
really really interesting things that
people are doing with active inference
this is purely like how do you build a
system that does this so the synthetic
came out of trying to say well this is
us trying to build engineering tools for
active
inference very fascinating just in how
you framed it there it made me think
about the engineer of a bridge and on
oneand they have colleagues in physics
and
Metallurgy and gravity and the basic
physical phenomena and then on the other
hand they have colleagues who have
bodies May care about the ergonomics the
cultural components of the architecture
and so it's like
engineering actually intermediates
between in this case the basian
mechanics and on the other hand
biological systems of interest for
active
inference yeah you could say you could
say that view right um because this is
just a way of doing active inference on
graphs if you want to come along and and
be like okay I think I can use this to
model something about the brain or I
think I use this to model something
about uh interpersonal relationships
whatever that's amazing
uh that is awesome all the power to you
but what you choose to do with the tools
is different to to to the tools itself
like if you have a hammer you can use to
carve out a beautiful sculpture you can
use it to build a bridge but a good
Hammer is still going to be a good
hammer and all we're doing here is
building
hammers
cool okay another question you mentioned
the sprawling
graphs so how could you connect what is
enabled with this work to ecosystems of
shared intelligence and maybe even like
the internet of things like
iot so that's that's one of the things
that
um uh it's that I would like to see
happen at some point um because if you
have um the representation of inference
problem as being distributed over a
graph and you can do things
asynchronously when you pass
messages you can run these notes anywh
this is just an abstract thing so I can
have um say a drone flying around that
runs its own generative model and sends
messages back to some other
thing uh that then sends messages back
to some other thing that communicates
with my phone and my fridge and my
pacemaker um but as long as all the
messages sort of are taken care of and
all the little local computations work
then effectively it's going to be like
just doing inference on a really really
big model so one of the things that we
we uh wanted to do with the the
designing ecosystems of intelligence
paper is sort to try and push this idea
that intelligence something that does
inference and react probably to its
environment in nature it's a distributed
thing you know um the whole of humany is
way more intelligent than I will ever be
uh many many people are and which trying
to to a scientist put stuff into this
shared pool of knowledge but even the
intelligence that I claim is inside my
head it's really made up of a network of
neurons that are interacting and doing
things together and each neuron is made
up of a whole bunch of component parts
and so on and so forth or you know like
ants doing interesting things when they
swarm around and
coordinate most of the types of
intelligence that we see in nature is
actually distributed
already and moving to this idea of
distributed inference and distributed
message passing on on very very large
graphs that that do things
asynchronously is sort of our attempt
saying well if intelligence is
inherently
distributed and we can we can cast
intelligence as this type of inference
problem we should build our architecture
should build our
intelligences in a way that matches us
we should build them as big distributed
systems and once they have big
distributed
systems um we should get all the uh I
mean then we can use all these tools to
uh to figure out what all the the local
parts do and make sure that don't have
to write out schematic for the whole
system just take care of everything
locally around your little bit and all
the communications and if everybody does
that and we're
good well I hardly concur with the
distributed intelligence and when I see
this kind of engineering work it's like
like the idea that all intelligence is
distributed it's not the end point it's
not a hot take it's not where the
discussion ends it's like the first rays
of light of the discussion beginning and
so that's why there's so much to do on
on the formal side but obviously on the
application side okay next questions
from the chat wter
asks how straightforward is it to
develop algorithms along this
perspective
can I build an agent within a
day um yes you can uh because we put
this in rxn first so far it's not in the
the mainline Branch but the
constructions like the nodes that we
used uh to do our experiments are
publicly available as a repo that's
GitHub biab life L
aif where you can find these things in
the interface with uh RX and
the toolbox that's developed in BIOS
lab um so yeah the tools are there they
need to be polished a little bit but
they're there you can build an agent in
a day if you know how to to work with RX
and fur otherwise it might take you two
because you spend one working through
the
demos yeah I mean could you maybe go
into a little more about what bias lab
is doing with Julia and reactive message
passing RX and fur
yeah of course so um caveat um there are
people who are better at RX and fur than
I am Dimitri payv uh sort of the main
architect behind it and is a beast of a
programmer um so the the the majority of
the grunt work uh has been done by by
know other really really talented people
in in buyers lab so RX and fur is a
toolbox for doing message in based
inference minimizing constraint B free
energy and Factor
graphs um and it does so by marrying uh
message passing and reactive
programming reactive programming is this
idea that instead of you actually we can
we can do this a little bit here instead
doing something like this where I
pre-specify a schedule I write out all
the messages that flow on my
graph um I can say well any node is just
going to listen to all the incoming
edges and say if I can send a message I
will send a message if I can send a
message I'll just wait for all the
information to be available until I say
something um and if you do that and and
you can do that in sort of a a reactive
way that basically gives you a way to
specify a problem as you know your
inference problem with your constraints
and your Factor graph and everything
hook it up to a sensor in the ideal
World hook it up to a sensor and then
whenever you get observations coming
in um that will trigger your inference
uh just just when it
happens and the sort of way that things
flow on the graph will be data driven
rather than something that I as an
engineer specify which again it's
something that I like because the less
work I have to do um the easier it is
for me to get stuff
done yeah even as a non Julia expert I
believe this is a massive step for
active inference even with message
passing you're going to be in a
situation if you can't use reactive
message passing where if you have two
sensors of different frequency you
either choose to basically have to waste
clock Cycles calculating updates at a
faster rate than the slower sensor or
coar grain or throwaway samples from the
faster sensor so having this kind of
like just in time logistical information
supply
chain has very very large
performance improvements with some or
all of the same formal guarantees and
it's going to be especially important if
there's an ecosystem of shared
intelligence where components are active
at different times or have
asynchronous or that kind of
concurrency in effect which is just
basically real
systems yeah exactly because you and I
don't have like guess set schedule and a
set way that inference is done we React
to what comes in in and then we plan and
then we do things sort of in in real
time um and the beauty of of doing it in
this way and when everything is local is
that even as you go to to larger graphs
with things happening asynchronously you
inherit a lot of the same convergence
guarantees um so basically as you run
more
messages your inference of your free
energy is never going to get
worse it might you know something might
happen like we saw these spikes uh if
you get information data that's not
predicted but as you run more inference
it's never gonna it's never going to get
any worse so you can run this part a
little fast and this part a little
slower and you
know so still going to end up uh having
this nice nice smooth
curve yeah it's kind of like a net a net
that ratchets
everywhere yeah like it's it's it's a a
a large distributed system that reacts
acts to data and reacts to the world as
as things happen
um and in RX and fur is just being an
engineering tool for building that if
you have that as your vision you need
something that does it uh and that
that's what IX infer is is attempting to
be cool so maybe one more question and
then we'll we'll close for that one okay
upcycle Club
rights simulated analing including
Quantum simulated analing is considered
a metah heris do you use any types of
metah heris discs in synthetic active
inference
agents um not yet I'm not familiar with
Quantum simulated analing so I I can't
really speak to what it does um but the
thing that's different about this
approach to active inflence as opposed
to many other approaches is BAS
basically that we can do things locally
on the graph and we have these backwards
messages um I'm sure you can combine
that with uh a Quantum simulated
kneeling approach somehow uh and if you
find a nice way of doing it I would love
to see it uh but it's it's not something
we've done yet
now cool
well this was awesome it was very
relaxing and evenhanded
even even though it builds on so much so
it was an epic
presentation and I think sets us up
really well for DOT two when we talk
about what happens
next now that the dot one is in the
books yeah had a great time and I'm glad
you found it relaxing because uh I think
it was a bit most stressful over
here maybe receiving the messages
receiving the messages is easier than
sending them
maybe yeah but like thank you this this
was great um I thoroughly enjoy
this cool so thank you everybody for
watching and like leave a comment if you
have a question or if you're around in
time then maybe get in touch and join
55.2 so thank you
Magnus farewell
you
bye